<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: thoughts | Scott Cheng]]></title>
  <link href="http://scottcheng.com/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://scottcheng.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-15T17:35:28+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://scottcheng.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Cheng]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Grad Application Reflections]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottcheng.com/blog/2013/04/grad-application-reflections/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-15T15:41:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottcheng.com/blog/2013/04/grad-application-reflections</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago I accepted the offer of admission to <a href="http://cs.stanford.edu/education/masters">Stanford's MSCS program</a>, which concludes my graduate school application process. I'd like to record some key reflections that I have on this process. The following is based on my experience of applying for Master programs in CS / HCI, but should apply to applications for other degree programs as well.</p>

<p>Rule #1 for fellow Chinese applicants: <em>no agencies whatsoever</em>. I know you probably heard this from everyone, but I'd say it again. If you want to get in a good program, get your own hands dirty, and don't depend on others. Yes, going through the entire application process can be excruciating, but it's worth it.</p>

<p>Really know what you want from grad school, and build up your profile and application package accordingly to support your purpose. I'm a big believer of going for what you love, and grad application is no different. If you know exactly why you want to study in a program, you probably have a much better chance than many of your competitors. I've seen people who don't have a dream school. I've seen people who apply for a program because everyone else does (they aren't even motivated enough to read the program's admission FAQ). I've seen people who choose to study abroad because their parents tell them to. How can they convince the admission committee that they are motivated to succeed in the program? How can they possibly tell good stories in the Statement of Purpose?</p>

<p>Research your target programs. Are their any interesting faculty that you might want to work with? What tracks / courses do they offer that interest you? Anything about the university / department / location that attracts you in particular? Again, know what you want from each of your chosen programs (though your rationales are probably similar to one another), and make it clear in your application materials.</p>

<p>Spend solid time on your essays. Vince Gotera <a href="http://www.uni.edu/~gotera/gradapp/stmtpurpose.htm">said</a>, "The Statement of Purpose required by grad schools is probably the hardest thing you will ever write." I kind of agree. Nobody is born knowing how to compose good grad school essays. Before you start to prepare the essay, read what others say about it (you can find <em>a lot</em> online). When you are happy with your draft, ask people to read it, especially experienced people. If you are able to find good hands, you don't need to ask too many people, because one sophisticated reviewer can be more helpful than ten novices. Based on my experience, two types of people might be good helpers here: (successful) former applicants, and professionals who help students apply. I was fortunate to receive help from both these kinds of people: my girlfriend Ivy who got into Stanford Graduate School of Education last year, and Joanne who has many years of experience helping people apply for college. Though undergrad application is quite different from grad application, Joanne's expertise of SoP critique made a tremendous difference to many aspects of my essay. Now you have the feedback, revise, even rewrite. I made three major revisions before I finally got my SoP in good shape.</p>

<p>These are what I have in mind for now. Graduate school application is really all about how much you <em>want</em> to get in your dream program. If you <em>really</em> want it (and, of course, work really hard for it), chances are that you'll eventually get it. Where there is a will, there is a way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Learned as an Interviewer]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottcheng.com/blog/2012/10/what-i-learned-as-an-interviewer/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-20T01:18:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottcheng.com/blog/2012/10/what-i-learned-as-an-interviewer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I got an unexpected opportunity to interview some applicants for <a href="http://www.beijing3ds.org/">a startup event</a>. It was a unique experience that gave me a fresh perspective, and I'd like to share some of my discoveries as a first time interviewer (may sound extremely naive and stupid to you :p).</p>

<ol>
<li><p>An applicant might expect the interviewer to be familiar with everything in his application packet. I suppose I totally should, if I want to be a nice interviewer, but the fact is that I'm simply not able to bring back all the details of the guy sitting in front of me right after the previous one had left, when I have to talk to 6 applicants back-to-back in an hour. Point is, if there is something important in your materials that you think would significantly increase your chance, be sure to bring it up and remind the interviewer of it -- he might miss it otherwise!</p></li>
<li><p>As recruiters, all we really care about is whether an applicant <em>fits</em> the position. In other words, whether you'll excel at the job, and whether you'll be happy doing it. Some folks in my pool appeared very sophisticated at what they do, but failed to demonstrate the skills and qualities that we were looking for, so we had to reject them. Also, it's totally cool to have hobbies (music, sports, etc), and I'll think of you as an interesting person, but it doesn't make up for your aptitude (if you lack it), and doesn't have much to do with your chance of getting in.</p></li>
<li><p>Passion and motivation can be very appealing, and it's quite easy to tell whether they are genuine or not.</p></li>
<li><p>For the inexperienced: proficiency matters. It's definitely important to be a fast learner, but relevant experiences tend to be more impressive. Of course there has to be a first step to any new field in life, in which case it helps if you have taken the initiative and got some preliminary experience or research on your own, which also reflects motivation.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tags and #Hashtags]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottcheng.com/blog/2012/07/tags-and-hashtags/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-30T15:54:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottcheng.com/blog/2012/07/tags-and-hashtags</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://karrisaarinen.com/">Karri Saarinen</a> from <a href="https://kippt.com/">Kippt</a> <a href="http://blog.kippt.com/2012/07/17/tags-are-here/">hates</a> <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tag_(metadata)">tags</a>, and brought <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hashtag">#hashtags</a> to his bookmarking service.</p>

<p>I do agree that hashtagging is superior to tagging in some way. Hashtags can be defined right inside the item body, whereas tags are conventionally separate from the content. So instead of noting "Nice color scheme" and tagging "color scheme", I can just write "Nice #colorscheme". For a brief note on a link, in Kippt's case, this simplifies the bookmarking workflow. However, is hashtagging universally applicable? Imagine taking an detailed lecture note in Evernote, and hashtagging some keywords which are scattered over the 1,000 words. See the point? <strong>Hashtagging is good only if the content is short</strong>. It's perfect for <a href="https://support.twitter.com/articles/49309-what-are-hashtags-symbols">Twitter</a> and <a href="http://help.instagram.com/customer/portal/articles/95731-tagging-your-photos-using-hashtags">Instagram</a> for this very reason.</p>

<p>Besides that, hashtags and tags are almost the same thing. Karri says users should not be required to <em>"describe the content"</em> with tags, but lets them <em>"channel or filter"</em> the links with hashtags, which sounds pretty messed up to me. Tags and hashtags are both created to <em>describe</em> the content, and can both be used to <em>channel or filter</em> information. Describing comes in when you attach the tag / hashtag to an item, and channeling and filtering come in when tags / hashtags get indexed and become searchable. These are two intrinsic properties of <em>both</em> tags and hashtags.</p>

<p>Though hashtags can be a good choice for Kippt (since bookmark notes are usually short), they are not making the most of it. One important reason is that hashtag list is missing. I cannot find my frequently used hashtags; I cannot find any of my hashtags. I can only search them. But how is searching a hashtag anything different from searching the keyword without that hash? Well there <em>is</em> a difference: searching hashtags requires strict match, meaning you have to get the entire hashtag right before you can find what you are looking for.</p>

<p>Karri also disputes tags because some tags only have one item in them. Yes it happens, but how does hashtag alleviate the problem in any way? It makes things worse if Kippt does not prompt my existing hashtags when I hit # (and in fact it doesn't; Evernote does good on this). Am I expected to magically remember the entire set of my Kippt hashtags, or am I expected to log into Kippt and find out whether I used #idea or #ideas in my previous bookmarks every time I add new ones? If I don't, I'll end up having multiple synonym hashtags, and bookmarks that belong to the same channel fall apart.</p>

<p>To make tags or hashtags work efficiently in an information management system, <strong>they have to be listed, and they have to auto-complete</strong>. Twitter doesn't list hashtags or auto-complete them because <strong>tweets aren't meant to be managed</strong>, at least not in the way bookmarks are. In other words, the purpose of hashtags in Kippt and in Twitter are fundamentally different.</p>

<p>Karri is right that tags are not ideal for "channeling and filtering" information, but it's not because they are inherently broken or they miss a hash, but because they are often not used in the optimal way. It's okay to have synonym tags, and it's okay to have some one-item tags. We are not born librarians, and we are not supposed to precisely categorize stuffs the first time they land in our collection. But we should <strong>revisit our tag list</strong> (or tag hierarchy in Evernote). We should keep them organized by merging synonyms and by removing the rarely used and the meaningless. <strong>Our desk needs to be tidied regularly, so does information</strong>. We need to remind ourselves to come back and put things in order every once in a while, and we <em>need an easy way</em> to put them in order.</p>

<p>P.S. speaking of Kippt, I suddenly realized a couple of days ago what Jori Lallo meant by <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2012/06/14/yc-backed-kippt-goes-collaborative/">creating GitHub for links</a> -- make lists just like repos! Now Kippt lists are already collaboratable and watchable, let's see when they'll become forkable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
